but actually I've got an idea Joel
here's what we're going to do for the
rest of this episode okay this is we're
going to turn this into another versus
episode we're GNA we're GNA we're going
to turn this into a hacker versus
developer episode the right way and the
wrong way yeah and we're GNA say okay
Justin says this is a vulnerable code
pattern and Joel says well there's
there's a little bit of nuance to that
so there's a way to do
this
[Music]
[Applause]
hey guys real quick I want to remind you
about the critical thinking Discord
Community there's been a ton of great
activity on the chats lately people just
kind of shooting the breeze to drop in
New hacking tips and advice uh sharing
cool research that sort of thing uh so
it's definitely something you're going
to want to get in on if you haven't
already also we've got the subscriber
tiers in place now which will give you
access to really cool things like Master
Class AMA uh just random scripts that I
drop it's kind of like our Inner Circle
um so if you want to get in on that
please do we would really appreciate it
also it helps support the show so if
you're interested in any of that head
over to cb. show Discord to join the
community today and we'll see you over
there all right back to the
show boom boom boom we're rolling yo yo
yo how's it going pretty good dude lots
of lots of lately prepping for this live
hacking event coming up trying to knock
some critical thinking stuff out of the
way get some uh you know long-term
projects finished up so I can get in the
zone and do the hacky
hacky yeah same dude same I've been uh
I've been trying to block out some time
and and get prepared and it's uh
everything's been coming at me sideways
lately so hopefully hopefully it's all
come down now hopefully so hopefully so
um tell me a little bit about the
scraping project you were doing dude
sorry I just just like I didn't get my
breath breath straight there for a
second um tell me a little bit about
this uh this scraping project you were
doing dude because uh you posted about
it on Twitter looked pretty cool I want
more data man it it seems like a really
good uh a good place to do some bug
Bounty
analytics yeah yeah so um I was talking
with nagly um I'm trying to pull up the
data on my other computer here really
quick um I was talking with Nagle about
um you know just some sort of different
program statistics that we could look at
and one of the things that he mentioned
was that we should take a look at 90day
total bounties paid um and I think one
of the areas where hacker one doesn't do
a great job of data like visibility is
sort of like program data visibility for
hackers yeah um so like there's no real
way to sort of search or view this sort
of data across all programs as a hacker
um I don't really think they have a good
way a good incentive to reveal that data
to be honest um so that's probably why
um but uh so I wrote a quick little
script that basically just like pulls
all of my private programs and my public
programs that I'm on and it pulls down
all the ones that have exposed their
total 90day bounties some of them
haven't um and then basically just shows
me them um and it was really really
interesting actually the the data that
popped up because it wasn't quite was
what I was expecting I don't really know
what I was expecting to be honest um but
when I started to look at it um I mean
there's some really big discrepancies
right off the bat um I can't really name
too many of these because I also don't
know which one off the top of my head
are public or private right but what I
will say is kind of similar to what what
I found in the Tweet which is that um
you know I I'm on about 600 uh total
public and private programs okay um it's
not you know all of them it's not it's a
pretty decent cohort but um based on
what ybert was saying in uh the replies
it's probably about half of them um or
maybe even L than
half um and so uh from the day that I
have um about give or take 560 of them
um show their total bounties uh so you
know 40 or 50 of them don't reveal it
some of them I I think one of the ones
off the top of my head that doesn't do
it that's public let me just double
check
is
not bad okay I'm glad I didn't say it
it's not
public so there are a couple of them
that don't don't reveal their 90day
Bounty statistics which I I feel like
that's kind of like I don't know that
that's kind of a sketchy move to be
honest like if you're not revealing your
90-day statistics then I'm kind of a
little bit like like why why are you
doing that why you hiding that it it is
a little bit weird I'm not really sure
what the motivation would be to hide
that stat um
like I don't know I I think one
important thing to say is that like I
don't want to put too much weight on
this stat because we've talked about
this before like I don't think programs
really should be paying a lot of money
like I think that's kind of a bad signal
anything so um paying a lot of money is
like kind of a pro and a con but um I
think from the hacker perspective this
is one of the things we care about
because we want to see where programs
are active and um you know who's paying
a lot uh right now and you know maybe
why are they paying a lot or something
that somebody's exploiting all that kind
of stuff there's a lot of interesting um
sort of data points that you can pull
out of it yeah what are you thinking
about doing with that data are you GNA
you know I know there was some talk of
put putting it into a bot or something
like that but I don't know would you do
like a like a daily report or something
like that of like oh there's been a
bounty Spike over on this program or you
know something like that or what kind of
ideas did you have for that yeah that
might be what I'd do like maybe maybe
the right way to do this is to monitor
for programs that
um have large spikes relative to their
current or you know large payouts that
are relative percentages to their
overall bounties um that could be
interesting and and notify like hey this
program just paid out like
proportionately a large Bounty uh
compared to what they have been paying
or something like that and then maybe
that's an interesting place to take a
look maybe they rolled out some features
somebody found something and you can
jump on that bandwagon yeah I wish I
wish uh I wish it was more like the
hacker one live hacking event
leaderboard dude where it's like as soon
as the Bounty hits like the total goes
up and stuff like that cuz then you
could do some some stuff like okay you
know they just paid out we know right
now that they just paid out a 50k Bounty
or something like that let's go you know
check out this program because they're
paying a lot of money um right so yeah
that that could definitely be
interesting I I definitely looking
forward to see what you do with it I I
hope you you put it in the the ctvb
Discord man because I think I mean you
know I've got some bots in there that I
haven't fully released yet that I'm
thinking about releasing we'll see we'll
see if they keep on turning out bugs I I
don't know it's I need some
incentivization but um I've got some
Bots that that I i' would like to to
integrate you know into the community
and I think the statistic piece the data
scraping and and analytics of hacker one
programs could be really cool obviously
you're going to have to find you know
the ones that are just public and just
do those um or you can hash the name or
something like that insult it in some
way or yeah I don't know it could be a
little tricky but yeah yeah for sure um
so the other thing I wanted to mention
was um when we were looking at like
overall like numbers and stuff um like
who's paying what and how much and all
that kind of stuff one of the really
interesting thing is um you know when we
were looking at sort of like the total
bounties paid by like programs under a
certain threshold so first we were
looking at like you know who's paid less
than 10K or who's paid more than 10K um
and when you look at like who's paid
less than 10K it's 60 to 75% of programs
umut man you'd think like wow okay
that's not a lot and even if you add up
the
totals um it isn't a lot like the all
the programs that I'm on again like this
is a a smaller subset of all the
programs but of the programs that I'm on
the ones who are paying less than 10K
total about 12% of the total bounties
over the last 90 days again out of my my
data that I have and then the top 10
programs are accounting for like 50% of
those B wow so you know the top 10 are
doing 50% of the bounties and everybody
under 10k is doing 10% of the bounties
um and everybody under 10k is 75% of the
total programs so you know the top 25
are doing 90% of the bounties the top
sorry the top 25% are doing 90% of the
bounties and the top 10 programs
individually are doing 50 % dude sounds
like uh sounds like a a chart of the you
know wealth distribution in America or
something like that you know like like
it's pretty it's pretty gnarly but I
mean I guess we see those sort of
systems in pretty much every environment
where you know it it's pretty much
classic 8020 rule here of like you know
the top 20% or in this case you know
maybe the top not even 5% probably 2% I
have have you know 50% of the bounties
paid it's pretty crazy yeah absolutely
absolutely and so y ybert followed up um
on my tweet and said that uh it was
pretty interesting data and that the
data that I had scraped was actually
about half of the full data so I I I I
said I was curious how much like how
close my percentages were yeah to like
real world real world you know if you
scale it up sort of to the to the other
half that I'm missing um and he said
directionally it seemed correct so that
I I thought that was quite interesting
but he also mentioned this chart I'm not
good with you know chart names and I
know like the basic ones but he
mentioned it was a power law
distribution and I looked this up and it
definitely seems like a pretty close
representation where essentially like
it's very very um uh you know High sort
of you know 8020 basically like what you
mentioned I think it's the same thing
um the the 8020 rule Power log graph
type you know yeah so the ones where it
it does that like in the very beginning
gets very high and then steeply drops
off
yeah wow that that's definitely that
definitely represents the situation so
what kind of what kind of takeaways do
you think you know Hunters can can have
from this I mean is the takeway to focus
on a big program if you really want to
get a lot of money out of it I don't
know yeah so I think there's there's a
couple really interesting things one one
thing to remember is that you know like
I said 75% of programs right now are
cover for about 10% of the bounties
which means that there's probably
actually a lot more juice to be pulled
from that area um yeah those top 10
programs intuition there okay right like
the top 10 programs are paying 50% of
bounty sure um but like you know you
could hack on those and you could get it
it really just shows that they have
money but I think what what I'm more
interested in is the fact that you know
all of those programs that are paying
10K or
less um one they are paying 10K or less
right so that's like still pretty
significant bounties like you know maybe
it's only a couple reports um but they
have that kind of budget and they're
paying it out and secondly there's a lot
more programs in that cohort right so
we're talking about hundreds of programs
who are paying you know 10K or less and
10 programs who are paying hundreds of
thousands you know in the the top 10 um
yeah yeah so I I guess there's there's a
decent a decent takeaway there as well
as like you can focus on these smaller
programs they're not even paying out
that much right now there's not a lot of
competition on these guys and so you
know lower chance of dupes for sure but
it's a little bit you know there isn't
as much of a track record of bounties
being paid there and so for me that's a
little bit more of the indicator like
I'm less scared of dupes because my
methodology is not as dup Centric you
know dup dup bug Centric um and and you
know that's obviously I'm looking for
bugs that can be duped you know anyone
can my ey doors or you know anything
like that but like
um I guess for me I I kind of look for a
program that has a set track record of
paying money because I know that they
are more likely to pay you know um
versus programs that are like don't have
a track record but maybe you know the
competition isn't as severe but I think
that's also a function of being sort of
towards the top of the game um and if
you're you know a newer a newer hacker
it might be better for you to focus on
those smaller programs um you know make
that program your Niche make that
program your your your thing um and then
you know de develop a sense of presence
of like okay I can make you know three
or four thousand a month off this
program and then you know from there you
can
expand yeah and you know it makes me
think uh I'll probably expand on the
script a little bit and I'll start to
look at some of the other data points as
well that are available from programs so
like maybe what's their average Bounty
over the last 90 days instead of just
the total as well um because if it's
like you know let's say they paid a
million dollars with the average Bounty
is500 well you know that says a lot um
you know maybe they're paying a lot of
bounties and they're just a large
program but most of are finding
everything's low right right and from
like a hacker perspective like I'm not
really sure what the right conclusion to
pull away from that is it's like should
I should you just hack on that and farm
lows and mediums or you know and you
know that they have a lot of scope or
should you you know look for the the
programs that you know paid 15K in the
last 90 days and they're just above sort
of that threshold um and they've got
some decent bounties maybe they have
some new scope or something I I don't
know yet I I haven't really figured out
the right way to make this sort of um
useful from a hacker perspective but the
data is there and I think just generally
speaking like when I look at these list
of programs especially like the top 30
um you know they're they're they are big
programs that most people have heard of
that um maybe I mean a lot of them have
run live hacking events that's for sure
yeah I can read off some of them like
number 17 Uber uh
number number 15 get lab sorry might
have to B that I don't know if that
one's public that's fine we'll bleep
that the one that I that I yeah that'll
be easy to figure to figure
out um number nine Airbnb um number 12
Yahoo so yeah I mean like a lot of these
are like pretty big programs in sort of
the top like 15
um either like past live hacking event
runners or like current live hacking
event Runners um some of them are
private um like you know you know you
know number one program is a private one
you know what I'd kind of like to see
man is maybe if we could find some way
to show the
distribution of vulnerabilities a
specific vulnerability delegations that
a a program is paying out so I want to
know which program pays the most crits
and which program pays the most highs
you know and which program plays the
most mediums I think that would be
really valuable data and pretty much the
only way I can think of to do that is to
try to
correlate reputation increases on that
program's
leaderboard
to
severities does that make sense you
definitely do that you think so yeah so
I think yeah yeah so so the right the
right way to do that is
basically I mean It's tricky because you
would you would miss certain you would
miss some things but I think depending
on how many programs you're on you could
definitely do it at scale um so so the
model would basically be like this you
have um all your programs that you're on
you pull all those programs and when you
pull the programs you pull their
leaderboards with their top 10 hackers
you take those 10 hackers you pull their
profiles with their stats and then when
the program
gets
uh you well you'd have to monitor the
whole you'd have to monitor the whole
leaderboard yeah correct jeez so when
the program gets a new Bounty pay like
when they pay out a new Bounty you check
the leaderboard and you see who bumped
on the leaderboard if nobody bumped on
the leaderboard somebody who's not on
the leaderboard but maybe you could do
it with the thanks tab or something
something like that we so we we need to
or or here's an idea we could hit up
ybert and be like hey we want this could
you could you please do this that's
another possibility cuz he's been
cranking out stuff you know uh true so
that that's one option I I I think I
think that would be much more telling
right like I want to hack on the program
that pays the most crits you know like
like that would be that would be really
cool um and and and you know we can tell
from that that there's systemic issues
that they considered to be highs or
crits or mediums or whatever that
continue to make themselves present um
and so I think that would be a really
valuable piece of information um and and
you and you may be even able to
correlate it
with average Bounty range yeah because
you're just piecing together all these
pieces of information because the
average Bounty range you know it it
gives you a specific percentile and then
you might be able to use like a model to
extrapolate that data out to the rest of
the bell curve or whatever and and then
and
then map that onto the amount of
bounties paid over the past 90 days yeah
so like for examp people for example
number three in my list is Paypal uh
public program uh um so PayPal has paid
474k in the last 90 days um their
average Bounty range now the the
interesting thing is I don't know I
don't think average Bounty range is
actually 90 days is it it's overall
right ah yeah so that's that's even
trickier because you're not getting data
on your main number right yeah because
it says that their average Bounty range
is 1.9 to
4.1 which that's probably it's like
right in the middle of me for them or
the current Table um H interesting but
yeah we'll have to we'll have to think
through it see if we can figure out a
way to extra extrapolate that data um if
any of you guys in the uh in the
listenership here have any ideas on what
we could do with this data or um ways to
get that piece of data that I wanted to
tell how many programs uh you know how
many crits or highs or mediums or
whatever a program is paying definitely
uh hop into the critical thinking
Discord and drop drop us a note in the
Pod talk Channel um about that because
that would definitely be something that
I think would be interested in releasing
for the public um yeah I think there's
there's definitely some other data
points that we could you know pull from
not sure but I'll have to look I'll have
to keep looking Jo Joel is there's
nothing this is this is itching my brain
now we we nerd sniped Joel live live on
the Pod and now he's just staring
mindlessly into his computer screen um
no that's great man um all right well
let's let's pivot away from that topic
before you get into and and I can't pull
you out um next thing that I wanted to
talk about was the hacker notes launch
um a little bit of an announcement uh we
recently brought on grep me uh a hacker
by the name of grep me onto the critical
thinking team he'll be our writer and uh
he is going to be essentially listening
to the podcast episode before it
releases and then uh providing you all
with a uh hacker tldr of sorts um and
it's designed to be a little bit like
Tim Ferris verus five bullet Friday so
it's just going to be five bullet points
limited um at the top of the the blog
post and it's just going to note the
most important things from that episode
and then um it's going to take those
those most important things elaborate on
a little bit and then you know you can
just take those and run you know you'll
get a lot of the value out out of the
episode if you just read those five
bullet points and then beneath that
he'll elaborate a little bit more on the
content for those of you that um prefer
text based mediums versus audio or maybe
just can't get your you maybe your
headphones are dead or something like
that I don't know and you still want to
get access to the information um so that
should be that should be really good I'm
looking forward to seeing how he
continues to to push that out and I I I
think particularly just the the the five
bullet points will be helpful for people
that don't have time to listen to the
full
episode yeah absolutely I'm super
excited to see um you know where this is
going to go we we did a little bit of
this with the blogcast but I don't think
it was really um targeted towards the
right technical audience so hopefully
this is a little bit more of a technical
approach um you know sort of by by
hackers for hackers um and uh yeah you
know we definitely want to hear the
feedback about this so um you know as
you're reading through the through it if
you have any things you'd like to see
more of less of anything you'd like
changed um you know give us a shout in
the in the Discord we love to hear that
sort of feedback yeah yeah for sure and
if you're interested in getting this uh
as a newsletter um you can sign up for
that at ctvb doow uh or on blog.
criticalthinking podc
C.O um all right with that let's move on
to the next news item technically that
was the news section we didn't say that
that was the news section uh we just
kind of jumped right into it but um yeah
Joel gitlab cve man popped this past
week what's going on with that yeah yeah
yeah so there was a really interesting
uh I think it came out on Twitter
originally first um I saw it like
someone Dro yeah somebody just like in a
hacker chat was just like code block
like
get lab Zer day I was like oh wow okay
um so yeah there there was there's a
little bit of Buzz about this I did some
digging as well um because there was
some uh there was the it was announced
in their like release that there was a
security patch and then obviously
there's some buzz and whatever um
there's a repo created for it eventually
um I man to find the PR but the tldr uh
for this is essentially when you go to
reset someone's like you do a password
reset or like a password flow uh you in
the parameters you know how in in
parameters you can like array them by
putting like square brackets yeah in xww
form you all encoded you can kind of
like do square bracket and then like
square bracket or something like that in
order to indicate an array right yeah
either arrays or like IND like key
indexes basically you can you can do
both of them um so you can do that
basically if you do like user uh like
the parameter user and then the subkey
email and then you make make it an array
and the first value is like your target
user email and the second value is your
hacker email
and that's it my go it was really really
interesting I was actually looking
through the code to to try and
understand how this works and it's a lot
simpler um than it seems uh basically
what happened is they were taking this
parameter and they were sending the
password reset option uh they were
sending the the password re reset to you
know this email parameter problem is it
worked with an array like by default so
what's happening here is you're actually
giving an array of two emails the first
email is the valid email the second
email is your attacker email and what
it's doing is in the code it goes you
know through this whole flow and then it
goes and it it calls this function send
password reset instructions to email and
when it passes an email it's actually
sending it to an array of two emails so
it sends the same email two emails yeah
multiple two two directives or whatever
yeah exactly and so the first one like
you know it's going to check like is
this a valid account blah blah yes it is
because that's the first email but then
the second when it sends out the email
and it sends it to both addresses now
the attacker receives the password reset
link for the victim as well as the
victim receiving the password reset link
for the victim one I I cannot believe
that this existed in gitlab for so long
and that this was like because I've seen
this technique before you know I I've
seen people do this before in the past
and one thing that's always kind of
crazy to me is like how how does it
know oh maybe the specific token is or
the specific user specified is different
I don't I don't know but like how does
it look at that array of emails or
whatever and say okay the first one is
the user that we're going to you know
take over the account for and then the
second one is the you know and then
we're going to send the email to both
like I feel like it should fail when it
says look up the user whose email is
insert array here with two emails in it
you know like I don't know yeah it's
super weird um I was trying to find like
I I I didn't get to like dig deep deep
into how this works cuz like when it
sends a notification it has this like
type that it passes in like password
reset instructions and then yeah it does
some stuff so I think it has some sort
of like additional flow where it might
have gone wrong here but the commit that
they actually like changed to fix this
initially it's very very minimal it
literally just Mak sure um that it's
explicitly pulling out like the
the it's verifying the email right yeah
and like you know before it sends it
dude it's it's crazy to look at this
Ruby code man I I don't know Ruby just
always throws me for a loop and I guess
it they're using like it and then some
string and then do and then to to like
almost comment blocks on what it
specifically does which is like one
really cool for the for the impact of
like or for the purpose of like uh
documenting what the code is doing but
it just makes it really weird to look at
you know you're you're like is this an
if statement is this an IT statement it
do statement like why is this so
dramatically weird like so many
questions yeah there's a lot of like
weird Ruby isms uh that are like uh you
you'll like read a piece of code and
it's very like you said it's very
difficult to figure out what is like a
variable or where's like a class or a
reference is coming from and all that
kind of stuff so um yeah I was actually
I was looking at this this file to see
sort of like where it came from yeah um
and it seems that uh this was some sort
of new functionality that was added
within the last year to support password
resets from uh any verified email so if
you have multiple verified emails then
you can password reset your account from
any of those verified emails in just a
single one that might be what it is
because it might be like okay here's the
account and then here is the email I
want to send the interesting okay yeah
super super interesting well that's
that's a pretty gnarly bug man and I
can't believe how simple the PC was it
like fit in a short tweet not like a
long tweet like a like a very short
tweet um so that was that was cool to
see um and I spoke with a couple of my
Recon buddies and uh it seems like not a
lot of things are popping with it
actually because you have to have a
valid email associated with it which
shouldn't be that much of a problem I
don't think but um from what I've heard
you know people are getting on top of
patching it and uh there haven't been a
lot of uh public instances of it
exploited which is good to hear and sad
to hear you know I don't know got that
sort of pull of the heart in either way
when you're a bug bounty hunter or
offensive researcher so um yeah Absolut
is um all right so with that let's go to
the last news item of the day this one
was really exciting um this is from
Riley Goodside he is a researcher um on
some AI stuff at scale
Ai and and uh so you know we don't cover
a lot of uh AI related stuff here on the
Pod because it's just not a lot of
technical content to be honest like a
lot of it is like hey let me convince
this like semi you know sensient thing
to like do what I want it to do um you
know or render some markdown text or
something which is cool you know but
it's not like uh crazy um until this
came up which I think was a really
technical solution to a llm um related
uh vulnerability called prompt injection
which we've talked about in the past um
and essentially what it what it does is
uh Riley outlined the fact that llms are
able to perceive Unicode tag characters
um which are actually invisible
characters uh that represent all of you
know the normal English characters you
would use um and so there you these are
typically only used these tag characters
are typically used um following a flag
Emoji in order to create the flag for a
specific country so if you were going to
do the flag for the US it' be flag and
then the tag character U and the tag
character s um but since the llm is
parsing it from a you know from a text
perspective it's looking at the actual
characters not how they're actually
displayed it it's actually able to read
those and respond to those so you're
able to smuggle invisible pieces of text
into any llm prompt that's super
interesting the other place where I know
that these are used are for um the uh
the skin tone modifiers emojis
interesting same thing huh I I I hadn't
seen that so these seem like sort of
like a well I mean maybe like a tag or
like an a label you know for another
Emoji often used with other um Unicode
characters alongside other Unicode
characters and Riley actually figured
out a way that we can actually just take
over any prompt um using these so I I
think there's this is a pretty technical
solution um which I was really impressed
by and then of course our boy reso
jumped right on it and did a write up on
it did a video on it that was really
good explaining it and also released a
uh a python script a very short python
script that will allow you to take any
input and convert it into tag characters
um with just a simple um you know Char
conversion uh what is it like 0x e
000000 plus whatever the the ordinal uh
number is for that specific character
Point um so so very cool approach here I
think the biggest um attack that we'll
see with this will be uh embedding those
invisible characters into text that will
be placed into a prompt and uh will
bypass sort of the user being able to
see that they're actually pasting that
text into the prompt and result in in
prompt injection or indirect prompt
injection yeah it's really this kind of
reminds me of like the early days of
like sandbox escapes because this is
like you know it's it's kind of a lot of
what what this is which is right now I
don't think it it feels like a lot of
the AI companies haven't quite figured
out the right way to like systemically
deal with this stuff so it's a lot of
like oh [__] there's a hole here there's
a hole here there's a hole here and
they're just running around sort of duct
taping holes and like you know putting
temporary stuff in place and fixing
things wherever they come up and
eventually you know a little bit down
the line they're going to figure out the
right way to sort of deal with all the
CU this seems to be a pattern where it's
like you know stuff that's to the human
is like oh like this is crazy cuz like I
can't see this visibly but like I think
it's a little bit weird cuz what's going
on here is like those characters are
there they're just not visible because
they're not rendered by your browser
they don't have like a text
representation or you know one way or
another and so I think there's a variety
of different possible solutions that
could go in place you know like you
could make the browser render invisible
characters or you could have your site
not support invisible characters or you
know the LM like you know re writes your
input message to show the invisible
characters and or who knows like I think
there's a lot of different things but
none of them are super great um but but
eventually we'll get to some more
systemic systemic fixes I think it's a
little bit tricky you know to fix this
sort of thing at an llm level I believe
um we had some debates in the comments
with uh some random dude that was being
very obstinate excuse me um and but
essentially saying like reso mentioned
in here that it's it's very difficult to
fix this because
sure you can you can fix it at the API
level but fixing it at the llm level is
going to be is going to be tricky
because of how it perceives characters
and and that sort of thing and and some
of the good features of llms which is
they inherently understand Unicode they
inherently understand you know these
characters that have circles in them you
know or circles around them and that
sort of thing so how do you discard some
and discard the other um besides doing
it at the API level so that that'll
definitely be an interesting problem for
for those people to fix but for the time
being I think there's a lot of a lot of
cool applications here from a from an AI
perspective and I'm sort of wondering if
there's any other anything else that
this could be used with um I imagine
these characters will have Unicode
normalization happen to the actual
characters in some scenarios so maybe
there could be a situation where like um
you submit an a a email you know like
you apply to be in an organization or
something and the admin looks at your
name right or your your um your email
address and says okay uh you know this
is clearly Justin at you know safe.com
but it's actually safe you know
invisible character invisible
character.com and then when they add me
to the organization that Unicode gets
normalized and it add sends it to my
evil domain or something like that um
could be some interesting applications
there from just a web app perspective as
well yeah super interesting yeah so very
very very good stuff there um that's all
I had from the News section um with that
let us get into the topic of today's pod
which is vulnerable code patterns so um
sort
of uh I'm not sure the order that these
episodes are going to I think the the
order is that um this one will come
first so in the future there will be an
episode where we're talking about
WordPress uh WordPress plugins and a
bunch of like crazy bugs and stuff like
that that I've been finding and and that
uh the word fence team has been finding
and and uh lots of discussions
surrounding that it's a very nuanced
ecosystem and we provide you with a
really great um summary of how to look
at that ecosystem quickly and find bugs
that will affect your targets so that's
coming up but with all that knowledge
that I had to get in order to do that
episode I did a [__] ton of code review
in PHP um and so uh and I've been
teaching this code review to a couple of
my mentees and friends um and I realized
that there are some code patterns that
are just really common
that we kind of need to talk about and
and get out there and get sort of um
framework ised of sorts uh before we
actually in order to be able to see them
more easily when we look at code at a
glance because you for the experienced
eye you look at a piece of code and
almost in in an instant you can say okay
this is the structure this is the flow
you know these are the conditions that
need to be met um and I think the more
we can U framework eyes that that
thought that intuition uh the better uh
code reviewers we going to be um so
that's kind of what I'm thinking we got
how many of these do we have Joel see
one two three four six seven seven seven
or eight um various different code
patterns that I wanted to go through and
just kind of discuss and talk about
vulnerabilities surrounding those um so
so the one really quick I I wanted to
preface this because um when you brought
this up to me I thought it was an
interesting concept um and I
think there's there's some important Nu
oh uh oh got his fighting gloves on here
hold on let's
go and I think like I I do want to
encourage people to be like reading code
and like looking for code patterns and
like be able to identify that stuff but
I also want to encourage
the mindset of context is key okay and I
think like that's really really
important because you can take all these
Snippets of code and you can put them in
some random context that is not exposed
to the internet or it's not exposed to
the world or just happens in a box in a
silo and it's completely yeah it's like
not great coding practice but it's not
an issue um and so I think being able to
identify whether or not something's an
issue is the real challenge here like
yeah start the starting point is is also
tricky but I think like um you know this
is sort of it's not it's not the
equivalent but it's it's close to the
equivalent of just like contrl f like
eval and then just like anywhere you see
eval and like yeah Bell's bad but not
always um you know there there there can
be use cases or safe ways to use it or
whatever um so uh yeah these these
patterns oftentimes can lead to things
but the the context is really important
like you know if this isn't a plugin
like is that is that flow exposed or is
this just something that happens in the
background like you know H how is this
being used is you know one thing that
you mentioned was uh HTML decoding right
and like you see HTML decoding and
that's like a was that before or after
you called me a human semrep instance
Joel in our in our call that was before
and then I said this is semrep um
because yeah HTML decoding can be bad
but like how's it being used right are
they HTML decoding to log it in the
console or are they HTML decoding it to
put it in the HTML yeah I mean 100% but
like what I'm trying to highlight here
is that there there are some things that
actively undo whatever you've just done
for example let's just go ahead and jump
to number two first sorry sorry editor
that has to you know maybe put up the
little Graphics or something like that
but um we're going to jump to
sanitization and then modification of
data afterwards the the scenario that I
had for this was you have an input
parameter that you take from you know a
query parameter something like that you
run some sort of sanitization function
on it right this is something that
strips out HTML elements and that sort
of thing right and then you immediately
pass it to URL
decode that sanitization HTML function
has done effectively nothing in that
scenario because
you you can take everything that that
function does and Undo It by putting
that in an encoded format that then gets
decoded on the next line so so like
whenever you have these sort of Trades
off tradeoffs it shows that the
developer is not understanding something
and I think that's always a good and a
good indicator of where vulnerability
might be or at least a place to look a
little bit closer wouldn't you
agree just yeah yeah I mean it they're
good like starting points I think um
this is kind of my like this is my big
problem with semrep like searching is
that compared to something like code ql
which is more as
based um it's looking for something that
looks wrong right but it's not actually
smart enough to tell whether it is wrong
and so it leaves a lot of that manual
effort up to you and it can be timec
consuming I don't think it's bad I just
think it's like not the most efficient
way to do stuff um just kind of depends
on what what is available for what
you're doing like PHP for example
there's no cql support for PHP so you
can't use cql for that either you need
to you need to write your own tool or um
just get
started don't look at me like that snip
or or you use some GP it um yeah yeah
but um you know sanitizing HTML and then
you all decoding um I'm inclined to say
that there are probably cases where
that's not an issue but I no how could
this not be an issue if there's if
there's a a scenario where you either
the sanitized HTML call shouldn't be
there in the first place because it's
not doing anything and it's wasting CPU
Cycles or it's problem I mean it's it's
I mean not to say that it will result in
an issue you know they could URL decode
it and then say compare it to a you know
a string or something like that and then
make some decision based off of that
right you're not going to be able to
inject it or whatever but in the first
place they shouldn't be HML sanitizing
it in that scenario because if they're
just going to compare it to a string
anyway and then do some action it
doesn't actually there's no reason to
decode it or to to sanitize it in the
first place what if they decode it and
then sanitize the
HTML no of course that's the opposite
way right that's the right way to do it
you you you decode it and then you
sanitize so that you can if there's
another sanitize call after
this oh oh yeah I mean well you know
there is that possibility but then that
doesn't really fit the pattern you know
the pattern is that it you see some
sanitization that occurs and then
afterwards you modify that data and and
that's just a dangerous place to be
because like even with and we'll talk
about another one later with with
replace statements but you know you you
can you can affect the result of what
you thought you accomplished with the
sanitization call if you modify that
afterwards you know yeah I think the big
thing that I think modification is the
wrong word I think I think we you're
trying to get it is like a reuse of
attacker Control Data right so you're
sanitizing it and then you're decoding
that data again and it's still attacker
controlled right if you're modifying it
with something that's not attacker
controlled mod simply modification of
data that's been sanitized not
necessarily an issue if it's
modification with attacker Control Data
of attack Control
Data right it's about sort of like the
chain of custody of of the data right
custody the data I like that chain of
custody of the
data that's good right it's yeah you
want to be ensuring that like you're
actually still in control here right
like because at a certain point like it
might pass through a function like maybe
it passes through sanitized HTML and it
gets converted into an arbitrary PHP
object that's totally custom and it's
not actually a string and then when it
URL de codes it it like handles it
separately or something like I don't
know right like I think there are
potentially some instances but that's
like a really important thing to be
looking for is like where like do I
still actually control this data like
throughout these steps yeah I agree and
there's definitely Nuance to the
situation right like like
um like you said in the beginning and I
think your your main point here is
context is King and that you need to be
able to at the end of the day PC or GTFO
what does it actually do to affect the
application what I'm trying to get the
train my mes to do and also to um this
is an important part too what I'm trying
to formul formula formula formulate
formulate for formula formula eyes I
don't know it turn into a
formula is that is is that the word that
is a real word I've got two second
languages man I swear um but uh what I'm
trying to turn into a formula in my
brain is when I turn these into formulas
it makes my brain see them better and it
makes if be less intuition based and
more principle based and so that's what
I'm trying to bring to the peeps here um
and and then also you know to have these
trigger you to take a second look
because when you're looking at a code
base you're SC you know you're scrolling
through a ton of code your eyes are just
you know like reading everything you
need to know when to say oh that's
something interesting and that's a very
valuable skill in code review I think so
yeah and I think like this is kind of
like the nuclei or the htpx or whatever
of like why do you keep comparing me to
tools
dude I'm just saying no no no no let me
let me let me expand because like
basically those tools are really good at
taking large inputs and helping you
narrow down by like signal by like
pointing out signals right like hey this
host is online or this is running Apache
or yeah um you know this is spring Boot
and here's the version and so you know
like whatever like and I think this is
kind of similar because you have too
much to look at like realistically you
could read through every single line of
every single plug-in on WordPress and
you could audit them all like that
and that's fine I'll see you in 50 years
like you know like it's you're never
it's never going to end like yeah um and
so you really need a better way to sort
of narrow it down which is kind of what
we're talking about which is like you
know okay I have this massive code base
where do I even look uh you know here's
like a couple interesting spots and
these aren't guaranteed uh to be
findings but they are good starting
spots and maybe you'll find something
else like you know along the way when
you're looking at that but they're
they're good sort of entry points to to
you know easy sort of things to take a
look at yeah and especially when code
reuse is a part of it too you know like
if this these flaws that I'm we're
getting ready to describe here are in a
function that is reused in multiple
spots throughout the application then
you can say Hey Okay this will result in
a vulnerability in XYZ scenario let's go
see if this is ever used in that
scenario and then you know you can kind
of reever work backwards from that code
reuse um starting point um right but
yeah I definitely agree with what you
said about about using this sort of as a
way to filter you know as an aquatone of
sorts now we got screenshots now we got
you know is the host alive sort of
scenario rather than all right let me go
knock on the door of every single port
um right right so with that all right
let's go back up to the first one the
first one is uh off check inside the
body of an if statement so this is
something that I've seen like is stupid
amount it's kind of funny but like if
there's an if statement and then your
off check is inside of that if statement
obviously you can if you can control the
condition of the if statement you can
absolutely run whatever is outside of
that if statement or in the lse
statement um and so whenever I see an
off check inside of an if statement
where the condition is user controllable
I'm always like wait a second why what's
going on there and I always look a
little bit
deeper yeah yeah and so from like a
developer perspective I think like
there's a couple of different instances
it's not always bad thing like sometimes
it's you know you want it to happen only
in certain case and you want everything
else to still happen so like maybe it's
normal intentional functionality yeah
yeah and it also could be that um
there's this this coding practice called
dting where basically instead of um you
know if you imagine this if statement if
you flip it and you do if not get and
then you call do something else and then
otherwise you're calling you know check
off you can sort of flip your if
statement and you can do certain logic
inside the if statement and then just
you know after the if statement you just
do everything else right um
inside a check off you know
theoretically there's a return statement
here somewhere or an exception or
something that's supposed to cause the
outer function to break out in a in a
bad case realistically maybe probably
not doing that I mean looking at this
code certainly doesn't seem like it's
being caught anywhere this is just a
little bit of code I wrote so that I can
help you visualize you know what we're
talking about but actually I've got an
idea Joel here's what we're going to do
for the rest of this episode okay this
is we're going to turn this into another
versus episode we're gonna we're gonna
we're gonna turn this into a hacker
versus developer episode the right way
and the wrong way yeah and we're gonna
say okay Justin says this is a
vulnerable code pattern and Joel says
well there's there's a little bit of
nuance to that so there's a way to do
this yeah it's called dting you know and
dting no that is an interesting practice
though and it definitely does make your
your um uh it can make your code more
readable and and shorter when you have
you say okay is this just a massive if
statement should I just invert this put
everything else on the outside and then
make a short if statement that catches
the scenario and exits if it needs to um
right but that exit is like the key
right like in order for you to be able
to Dent successfully it has to
essentially exit it has to bail out and
so if that bailout behavior is not done
properly or if it's like supposed to be
handled in a different function it's not
being handled in a different function
then it's not going to bail out right
and it's just going to keep going funny
if you look at number four now check for
bad pattern with an if statement but
then don't do anything to the control
flow that's exactly what we're talking
about there this is a scenario where
essentially you look there's an if
statement that's clearly used for
security purposes um and then you know
inside the if statement they're supposed
to be handling that bail that bailout
that error but sometimes they just like
set a set a variable to true or
something like that and then never do
anything else with it later and the code
continues on anyway um that's another
bad pattern that I've seen and that's
exactly what you're talking about right
yeah I mean I don't have a justif
justification for that one other than
like you know humans like developers are
humans too and the reality is that uh
just like everybody else they started
something and forgot to finish it or uh
you know they had a plan and and one way
or another the code still worked and uh
it was inconsequential the way they were
testing it but test case being yeah yeah
so that's another one to take a look for
you know whenever they're bailing or
whenever there's an
strategy in place making sure that
that's
actually killing the control flow of the
application um will result in in you
know some some valid code versus if it's
not killing it if it's setting a
variable then you still got to continue
to trace that flow even though they've
detected something bad and they're on to
us uh there still could be things that
you could do especially if there's a
sync in between you and the the you know
death that inevitably occurs due to your
bad input yeah um yeah or maybe they're
they they have that check and they set
bad equals true and then they do
something with it but what they do with
it isn't right or they or it's not
meaningful it's too late yeah or yeah
exactly like maybe they do something
else with your vulnerable data and it's
you know the bad check is already you
know hasn't happened yet yeah exactly
all right what do do you uh do you want
to pick uh up any of these or or no no
no we'll we'll do it this way and I'll
I'll say it and then you can you can
comment on it so next one next one on
the list is bad Rex I'm interested to
see how you
uh this is a losing battle how am I
supposed to defend someone not escaping
a DOT on a re I set I set you up for
failure here um but yeah so this next
one is sort of a a Rex based one which
is you know anytime you see Rex to be
hon for for any of you that are scared
of Rex and that have not taken the dive
to understand Rex fully you will get
such an Roi on this if you just Deep
dive Rex and understand it thoroughly
because so many people try to use Rex
for sanitization and for security and
man is a tricky to do right um so
definitely not not only that like I use
Rex for a lot of things I mean I use Rex
all the time for like just developer
flows or like pulling data out of you
know pipe a pipe like piping data
through bash and stuff just like pulling
different data points out and stuff or
manipulating data and all that kind of I
use Rex all the time like Rex is such a
valuable tool and the syntax is not
difficult like it's a little bit
daunting at first um we've talked about
this before probably Rex 101.com amazing
site like literally just take a Rex put
it in the website and then look on the
right side there's a there's a section
called explanation and it literally
walks you through every single part of
the Rex and says here this does this
it's looking and it in layman's English
terms explains exactly what that part of
the Rex is doing and then it goes to the
next part and says this is looking for
this and this character does this
modifier and it's looking for this this
this and this amazing tool
great very useful for Learning reic and
understanding like what is this thing
I'm looking at actually doing the other
side of that is you can use this start
writing your own Rex and in the test
string just like put your own data in
there and just start writing a Rex and
be like how do I select this data you
know I want to select because it
highlights the data you've selected too
and it's like
show yeah um you know definitely I'd
recommend taking some time learn about
Rex there's a lot of tools out there um
there's another tool we'll link it I
don't I'll have to find it
um uh this is your this is your re
strings tool yeah we've talked about
this I think once before on the Pod it's
that's a great tool too I haven't used
it quite as much I did put the um I did
put the Rex 101 in the link section by
the way oh cool um awesome but yeah so
you can drop that down there as well Rex
to Strings is also really cool it'll
it'll give you strings that match your
Rex um very helpful with regards to what
actually things you should be on the
lookout for when you look at a
um obviously there's this concept of
dots in Rex being meaning any character
and man did the Stars Al line when
people decided to make that the dot any
character and make dots the separator in
domains um one of the things that I just
Relish in my life like that sort of good
luck for attackers so anytime you see an
unescaped uh dot in a URL based reject
or in a domain based Rex you can pretty
much guarantee that there's something
you need to look into there's you like
that Joel did you like I didn't say good
I didn't say that there's any you know
that there's guarantee there's a vone
there there's definitely something that
you need to look into there yes
absolutely look into that and the other
thing um and it's mentioned here is like
the missing of the carrot and the dollar
sign which indicate the start and end of
line um depending on the context of the
data that's being passed in for the
match it might be doing a reject search
on you know everything the whole input
or whatever non-filter part and so if
it's not not specifically saying I want
the whole match to start here and end
here then you can match data within
other pieces of texts that may be
completely irrelevant so you can you
know a good example is you know
www.example.com do attacker.com yeah
right and and it's only looking for www.
examp example.com or we have github.com
on here but um yeah you know if it's
only searching for that and it's not
checking for the end of the line then
you can have stuff after it and before
it that can change the context of that
data and be used in different ways yeah
100% And so that that's a big one to
look at the the start and the ending
another one is that a lot of times
people just won't think about all of the
possibilities from a character
perspective so we talked in the past
about um what parts of the URL have what
impact uh on on you know what host the
request will be routed to in the end
we've got those the at sign that allows
us to add characters before the uh the
actual domain is is specified that can
be really helpful
um and then we've also got in the
context of URLs we've got
slashes you can use backslashes instead
of slashes um and a lot of time the
browser will natively convert those or
any um request sending tool you know
curl and that sort of thing we'll we
convert them as well a lot of times so
um you really want to think about the
edge cases the breadth of possibilities
you have from a p uh a character set
perspective and then also I this is sort
of only tangent related but I ran into a
situation where this was helpful the
other day you know some servers will
just accept the full path in url encoded
format so you could just you know
percent 2f ABC percent 2f you know one
two3 you blah blahy blah like that you
don't even have to have slashes in there
um and so that's another thing is you
know even if their code isn't doing URL
decoding you may be able to affect the
back end by sending those URL encoded
characters directly to the back end if
you're in sort of like an ssrf or
secondary context sort of
situation yeah yeah for sure um and one
thing I was I was thinking about as you
were describing that yeah um well two
two things one with the you know they
might their rejects maybe a little too
broad in terms of what they're expecting
so maybe they use dot Star right or
something like as just like a filler
right that's that's pretty common people
use dot star meaning any number of any
character but you know infinite uh from
zero to infinite um and the Rex uh two
string tool that I that will link down
below is a great tool for that because
you can take a Rex and you can put it in
there and you can see all the different
possibilities and that will really
easily identify like hey here's like a
weird spot where you can put a bunch of
different characters or here's a spot
where there can be sort of infinite
possibilities of things in between um
and and that makes it really useful
um oh what was I going to say well I
think I had it well I don't know where
you were going to go but where I was
going to go after you done going with
where you were going to go was um and
there's Nuance too to the star and the
plus sign right you know in that
scenario you know if you're using star
then you can just ignore that whole part
if you want to because zero it matches
the the thing zero times um and a lot of
times people will also use star when
they should be using plus to make sure
that there's at least one instance of of
the thing one to infinite instances um
versus zero to infinite instances so
that's another sort of gotcha in that
scenario does that does that trigger
what you were going to talk about or is
remember okay great yeah well it wasn't
related to that but um one thing that we
talked about in a recent episode was the
FR uh Rosen xss Challenge and this was
very related to Rex specifically and and
specifically JavaScript like Rex
replacement group name like special
naming things um so that's another thing
to keep in mind with reject specifically
in the context of JavaScript I don't
know about other languages if they have
support for it to that full extent um
like those different replacement groups
but uh I know that the the JavaScript uh
Rex replacement has all these special
capture groups that uh France pointed
out his excess challenge that can be
super useful that's a great Point dude
man like this was just so cool to see
that you could actually insert these
strings in the in the response you can
say you know things that match before
things before the match that we have
things after the match so freaking cool
um I cannot wait to exploit this more
and I'm glad you brought it up again
because it sort of refreshes that neural
pathway a little bit and makes it sure
it's in the Forefront of your head
rather than you know being being forther
back uh because that's such a cool thing
I'm GNA add it to the list here capture
groups see absolutely capture groups all
right last one on the on the RX list was
multi-line stuff um sometimes depending
on the Rex configuration uh and actually
I should add uh I should add Capital
capitalization
here uh capitalization and multi-line
both of those are things that are sort
of um Flags in most languages that you
can kind of turn on like do I ignore
case do I do this on a multi-line match
um and so if there if there is an
opportunity for multi-line input uh and
they're running something that just goes
through the first line then you may be
able to smuggle in a payload there um or
if there's something that they're
expecting to be a certain capitalization
and you can flip the case then uh it may
miss that Rex and uh result in you being
able to do some cool stuff so those are
some other things to keep in mind from
the Rex perspective anything else to add
there Joel no I mean I was just going to
say Rex 101 supports the flags um in
your regx thing there's a little you
click the little it's I think it's by
default it says GM G for Global M for
multi-line but it has a drop down of all
the different flags that you can use and
you can check them and it gives an
explanation of how they work um you know
we won't go too deep into all of the
nuances of Rex but I again I'd really
encourage go to Rex 101 and check out um
Rex if you haven't take taking a deep
dive into how that works and uh it's
definitely worth learning yeah one one
more piece there you know since we're
fanboying over Rex 101 right now um it
it's definitely the best idea to select
as granularly as you can the language on
the left hand side and the flavor
section um especially when you're
looking for exploitation because there
are specific nuances to various
different languages that you may be able
to you know pull out of there if you're
actually using the correct playground
for your regular expression evaluation
and and toying um so definitely don't
forget to do that as well um all right
next one on the list we already did the
bad the bad uh pattern one so we're
going to jump down to the next one oh I
love this one this is replace statements
for
sanitization um th you know replace
statements for sanitization are helpful
only in a scenario where you are
replacing one character uh and when
you're replacing a sequence of
characters obviously you can just sort
of Sandwich the thing in the middle get
something replaced and then you if it's
not recursive you won't you know you can
get the same flow of characters in there
so the classic example is dot dot dot
dot so four dots slash slash whatever
right and when they do a do do slash
replacement on that it'll remove the do
slash in the middle and the two dots on
the left hand side and the slash on the
right hand side will then become dot do
slash um and so since it's not recursive
you will just get that result in in your
resulting payload and be able to easily
bypass any um replace based uh stuff and
and and one of the things I've seen some
things do like for example the
sanitization functions in WordPress core
I was auditing those recently um they
will put annoying characters there
instead of just replacing it to nothing
uh you know they'll put an underscore
like a squiggly sign or something like
that and it's like well that Hecks up
the whole situation so if you see any
any stiz where the thing that they're
replacing with um is a is nothing uh
then you might be H able to do and the
thing that they're replacing is more
than one character then you may be able
to do something funky there yeah for
sure um I was going to say like the
recursive aspect that you mentioned is
is a pretty big caveat there like
definitely like if I think almost all of
these if you just put it in a you know
wow Loop that checks if it had any
Replacements and then you know exits out
whenever it's done replacing that would
fix it right like if you did a dot dot
slash and you just kept replacing until
it didn't replace anymore problem solve
um true but you know it can be very
difficult and the context I think you
know this is something that's not
context were right so like the big issue
of replacing a DOT SL is that that it's
not context aware like it doesn't know
what's around it it doesn't know how
it's being used and so like trying to do
that generically is kind of difficult um
you know if you say I don't want a dot
dot slash anywhere then you can
recursively replace it easy um but that
that's you know not always easy so yeah
I like that one that's a that's a good
one another Nuance while I'm thinking of
it is that um by default in JavaScript
uh do replace is the first match only uh
so if you take a string and you do
string. replace uh in JavaScript it only
replaces the first instance the right
way to replace every instance is that
you're supposed to do string. replac
with a Rex that Global matches it's
really it's very weird yep one two three
space one
two3
replace two3 with
squiggly check that out huh you know I
know I've seen that before but I don't
know that I've done okay so there's
actually a replace all function as well
um in JavaScript that will do all of
them um okay but uh the single rep man
okay anytime auditing JavaScript let me
just get this in my head come on I gotta
turn it into a formula in my head
anytime you see do replace in a
JavaScript
scenario alert alert in the brain okay
yeah the first parameter has to be like
a global Rex for it to actually replace
all the instances very interesting I
have uh now stored that in the hacker
brain it's going to stay there forever
now awesome very good um all right let's
see we oh okay so then we've got this
super weird one okay so this next one is
anything that allows you to call
functions or control code flow in an
abstract or uncommon way okay I know
that that's really out there but it
should make sense after I'm done
explaining it okay so PHP does this
super whack
thing where you can call string
and it's so dangerous it's so dangerous
and I actually this is one of my
favorite features of PHP but keep going
okay well you know I'm very excited to
hear about that afterwards uh but this
has resulted in multiple criticals for
me over the past uh couple months and um
essentially this sort of functionality
is just extremely dangerous for example
one of the common code patterns I'll see
is they'll say um in in PHP this you
know meaning the current class arrow and
then some string variable that you can
control and then call the function
that's associated with that string
variable and pass in something like the
entire
request uh you know dollar signore
request which contains all of your
parameters it's a map that contains all
of your parameters that you've defined
for the request directly into that
function um and so there's just so many
weird things you can do with this um I
can't I couldn't believe it when I saw
this you know actually coming up a
couple cple times it was really weird
but in in order to make this a more
general statement I I'm trying I want I
want to emphasize that any sort of
functionality in the app that will allow
you to arbitrarily call functions even
in a limited context um pretty weird and
should kind of set alarm off and make
you investigate
further yeah I think in standard
languages this would be like reflection
you know if you see like reflection
somewhere that's like pulling a method
by a name and then later calling it or
you know like that's kind of weird
behavior and this is what a lot of that
is um this is one of my favorite PHP
features cuz it's uh it's from a
developer side it's great like you know
gosh it's uh it adds a lot of
flexibility into your code because
normally yeah a lot of flexibility
that's fun way to put it well it's like
you know like the the the the real way
that you do this uh otherwise is like
you call eval and evals gross you know
so instead you get to do this
call yeah it's secret eval the method
has to exist exist you know but uh but
it's like yeah you can you it's nice cuz
for like deterministic code basically
you can have multiple functions and then
you can just be like this variable
equals you know this function name
otherwise this variable equals this
other function name and then you call it
and it you know there there is a use
case but uh it's pretty limited yeah
flexible flexible code for sure lots of
wiggle room in there lots of yummy
wiggle room for the
attackers um no it it is a cool feature
though and it is very convenient and
I've seen some very
um I guess efficiently written code
flows within the plugins that I've
audited because of that all right last
one on the list is sort of a type type
confusion sort of scenario and I
couldn't really figure out a way to
generalize this uh super duper well um
but if you're dealing with languages
that are not doing static typing then
you should always constantly be thinking
hey can I get another data type in here
you know what what happens if I turn
this thing that they're expecting to be
a string into an array you know and or
what happens if I if I you know try to
make them access the index of a array
versus an object or an object versus an
array right um there's just a lot of
flexibility here with type confusion
bugs and we talked about this a lot with
Matias on the episode in December um and
we can see sort of the gitlab bug that
we discussed at the beginning of this
episode very much resembles that right
they're expecting that email to be a
string and the fact that it was an array
caused Mass Havoc for the gitlab team um
so anytime you see non-static typing on
user controlled stuff that should set
off a flag too to just investigate a
little
further yeah absolutely um I
think uh not only is this good for like
debugging like um from a non- likee
coded auditing perspective we talked
about this a little bit where you can
you can fuzz like different data types
and parameters to get the server to talk
back essentially yeah um and that's
really useful but also you know like
this like the type confusion type stuff
where a lot of languages that are not
strictly typed or even if they are
strictly typed they have to convert the
input the inbound data into a strict
data type and so in order to do that
they have to manipulate the data one way
or another and that leaves some gaps for
how that data is being
interpreted between like when it's being
sent and how the servers actually
handling it and so I think depending on
you know the language depending on
whether or not it's typed depending on
how it's being some languages
deserialized some you know automatically
convert everything to Strings you know
it's definitely worth looking into
seeing what it's expecting and trying to
fiddle around with some other data types
and see what it does yeah yeah I totally
agree and one of the scenarios that I
that I think that this comes up the most
in is an INT sort of situation an
integer for an ID right the the person
has named the parameter record ID right
and they use that they assume that it's
going to be an ID in whatever context
they're in um and they but or and that
it's going to be a number and that that
they haven't done you know that int uh
typing Force typing um what what what am
I trying to say here Force typing what
what is uh casting yeah casting thank
you I couldn't get I couldn't get the
word they haven't done that casting
right um and then you know you provide a
string and if they in you know injected
into like a URL context on the back end
secondary context bugs that's that's
like the bread and butter for secondary
context bugs and then um also you know
this can cause problems in SQL context
as well traditionally um and then the
last thing that I wanted to mention here
is that there's a whole type of bug
class surrounding this sort of thing
that I think is not super really talked
about that I've been finding a lot of
stuff related to lately which is you
give it a a type that it doesn't
understand and they don't expect that
and it causes an error somewhere in the
code and it just breaks the whole thing
you know yeah um and so you know you can
turn this is a example literally like 10
minutes before we started recording uh
menty came up to me and said hey I've
got the C surf I can affect this really
sort of benign thing doesn't really
impact the application very much and I
looked at it and I was like Hey what if
we just give it some sort of what if we
just give it as if you know like what
happens then and we did and it just like
broke the whole page and and which is
the most important page on that whole
app um and so uh you know you go from
like having this very minimal impact
vulnerability to a type confusion to wow
everything panics and everything's
broken and now the page does
nothing that's super super good I like I
love that that sort of immediate impact
of uh being able to show the the type
confusion into something meaningful yeah
yeah dos is a really really good
playground for that all right man that's
all I had on my list any other ones come
to mind from you from all these or I
think I think we hit a pretty
comprehensive list yeah I think we hit a
pretty good list you know as we
mentioned these are like good starting
points they're not explicitly bugs but
they're they're they're a good way to
sort of narrow down your focus and um
you know as you were sort of doing
during this episode I think it's good
like as you read through code identify
those problems formulate them store them
in your brain figure out what like weird
things look like and then you'll start
to see more weird things exactly well
said man and with that we'll uh we'll go
ahead and cut it that's the Pome that's
[Music]
f